Charles Tomlinson Griffes Collection, 1768-2006, undated
Elmira College
Charles Tomlinson Griffes Collection, 1768-2006, undated
The collection contains letters, sheet music manuscripts, memorabilia and books from Griffes’ personal library that offer insight into the musical training and personal progression of Charles Tomlinson Griffes. The collection documents the formative years of Charles Tomlinson Griffes containing 28 original letters written during his early adulthood while studying music in Berlin, Germany, 1903-1906. The letters are addressed to Miss Mary Selena Broughton, his former piano teacher at Elmira College and his mother, Clara Griffes. A number of sheet music manuscripts of Griffes’ most important works: “Sonata,” “White Peacock” and “The Lake at Evening,” are included. The poetry that played an important role in Griffes’ musical process is represented in the collection by numerous books from his personal library.
8.75 linear ft.
Elmira College
Elmira College Archives, Gannett-Tripp Library, Elmira College, Elmira, N.Y.
Organizational Note:
The Charles Tomlinson Griffes Collection is organized into the following series and sub-series:
Series 1: Personal Papers [1903-1917, undated]
Sub-Series 1: Correspondence [1903-1906]
Sub-Series 2: Miscellaneous [1903-1917]
Series 2: Sheet Music [1898-1929, undated]
Series 3: Books from Griffes’ Library [1768-1917, undated]
Sub-Series 1: English, 1859-1913, undated
Sub-Series 2: French, 1836- 1917, undated
Sub-Series 3: German, 1863?-1913?, undated
Sub-Series 4: Italian, 1768-1911
Series 4: Materials published about Griffes [1903-2006, undated]
Series 5: Sound Recordings [1976-2003, undated]
unrestricted; reproduction and publication require additional approval
Charles Tomlinson Griffes was born in Elmira on September 18, 1884, in a house which stood on the corner of Main and Gray Streets…
Griffes’ father, Wilber Gideon Griffes, was associated with a gentlemen’s furnishing business while his mother, Clara Louise Tomlinson, had been at one time a so-called “selective student” at Elmira College.
Not until the age of eleven did Griffes begin to study the piano seriously with his sister Katherine. By the time he was fifteen he had exhausted his sister’s resources as a teacher and began to study with her teacher, the “Professor of Piano Playing” at Elmira College, Mary Selena Broughton. Griffes graduated from the Elmira Free Academy in 1903. Miss Broughton had sufficient faith in his talents to help underwrite a period of study in Germany for Griffes.
Griffes spent four years in Berlin studying piano, theory, and composition. For the first two years he was enrolled at the Stern Conservatory where he had as piano teacher a former student of Nicholas Rubinstein and Tchaikovsky. Griffes’ father died late in 1905 and when Griffes came back to Elmira in the summer of 1906 to visit his family, he gave a piano recital at Elmira College. The best known person with whom Griffes studied while in Berlin was undoubtedly Engelbert Humperdinck, the composer of the opera Hansel and Gretel, but Griffes had only a total of eleven lessons in composition with Humperdinck.
When Griffes returned permanently to the United States in 1907 he accepted a position as musical instructor at the well-known Hackley School in Tarrytown, New York. There he was to stay for the rest of his short life.
His four years in Berlin had revealed to Griffes that he would never have the technical dexterity necessary for performing in public on a large scale. Thus he dedicated himself to teaching and composing. In 1909 Griffes published five German songs, his first compositions in print. Slowly Griffes freed himself of the influences of his German schooling and began to compose songs to texts by Oscar Wilde, Sara Teasdale, and Sidney Lanier. Some of his most popular piano pieces date from the early period, 1910 to 1913.
In 1915 Griffes began what was to become his best known composition, “The White Peacock,” which had its first public performance the following year. It was published, along with three other works for the piano, under the collective title, Roman Sketches, Opus 7.
In Roman Sketches Griffes reached the high point in his preoccupation with Impressionism. In what is generally felt to be his greatest composition, the Piano Sonata composed in December-January, 1917-1918, Griffes found a voice unmistakably his own. It was performed for the first time by the composer in New York for the MacDowell Club on February 26, 1918, and although it was not well received by the critics, Rudolph Ganz did not hesitate to call it “the finest abstract work in American piano literature.”
Griffes’ last public appearance took place at Carnegie Hall on December 4, 1919, when the Boston Symphony conducted by the late Pierre Monteux, performed his symphonic tone-poem, “The Pleasure-Dome of Kubla Khan,” which continues to be a favorite with symphony audiences today. But Griffes’ frail constitution was already exhausted by his incessant activities of teaching, composing and performing. He took to his bed at the Hackley School shortly after the performance at Carnegie Hall in December. On January 16 he was moved to the Loomis Sanatorium in Loomis, New York, where he died on April 8, 1920, of abscesses of the lungs which resulted from influenza. He was buried in Bloomfield, New Jersey, where his mother then lived.
As Griffes’ biographer wrote: “Charles Tomlinson Griffes, lost in the moment of fulfillment, nevertheless made his small but imperishable contribution to the music of the world.” One can also agree with Mr. Maisel that, with the possible exception of Charles Ives’ compositions, Griffes’ Piano Sonata was “the first major utterance in American music.” (From Charles Tomlinson Griffes at Elmira College: A Festival on the Eightieth Anniversary of his birth 1884-1964, 1964)
Griffes, Charles Tomlinson, 1884-1920; Broughton, Mary Selena; Griffes, Clara; Composers, Basque; Letters; Pamphlets; Sheet music; Programs
The collection contains materials integral to understanding the life of Charles Tomlinson Griffes and includes letters, books and manuscripts. The collection documents the formative years of Charles Tomlinson Griffes containing 28 original letters written during his early adulthood while studying music in Berlin, Germany, 1903-1906. The letters are addressed to Miss Mary Selena Broughton, Griffes’ former piano teacher at Elmira College and his mother, Clara Griffes, and give insights into his evolving thoughts on music and his career path, from an initial desire to become a concert pianist, to his realized profession as teacher and composer. Critiques of local concerts, his musical scholarship and daily activities while in Germany are common topics of the letters.
In the collection are sheet music manuscripts for various compositions. Early compositions include: “Opus 2: Six Variations in B Flat Major” and “Four Preludes, Opus 40,” both written for Mary Broughton. The handwritten manuscripts for Griffes’ most important works during his creative peak are highlights of the collection: “White Peacock,” “Sonata,” “The Lake at Evening,” and “Sonata,” and lesser known works, “La Reveillon,” “The Rose of the Night,” “Lament,” and “Shojo”.
The poetry that played an important role in Griffes’ musical process is represented in the collection by numerous books from his personal library. The works are in English, German, Italian and French, showcasing Griffes’ affinity for languages.
The collection also contains scrapbooks of newspaper clippings, programs, materials from various events held in Griffes honor, recordings of Griffes’ compositions, several photographs and two original sketches done while in Europe.
- SERIES 1: PERSONAL PAPERS, 1903 - 1917
  - SUB-SERIES 1: CORRESPONDENCE, 1903 - 1906; This series contains 28 letters written to Miss Mary Selena Broughton and his mother, Clara Griffes. This sub-series is arranged chronologically. (Box-folder 1: 1)
    - Letter and envelope: September 6, 1903 -- Written on Central-Hotel, Bremen letterhead -- written to his mother from Berlin, discussing his studies and daily activities, including his rehearsal schedule, etc. [1903] (Box-folder 1: 1)
    - Letter and envelope: September 18, 1903 -- Written to Miss Mary Selena Broughton at Elmira College -- 10 page letter, primarily discussing his studies and daily activities, people he has met, etc. (1: 2)
    - Letter and envelope: October 18, 1903 -- Written to Miss Mary Selena Broughton at Elmira College -- 8-page letter, primarily discussing his studies and daily activities (Box-folder 1: 3)
    - Letter and envelope: November 18, 1903 -- Written to Miss Mary Selena Broughton at Elmira College -- 10-page letter, primarily discussing his studies and daily activities (Box-folder 1: 4)
    - Letter: December 6, 1903 -- Written to Miss Mary Selena Broughton at Elmira College -- 6-page letter, primarily discussing his studies and daily activities (Box-folder 1: 5)
    - Letter and envelope: December 21, 1903 -- Written to Miss Mary Selena Broughton at Elmira College -- 8-page letter primarily discussing and critiquing of concerts (Box-folder 1: 6)
    - Letter and envelope: January 4, 1904 -- Written to Miss Mary Selena Broughton at Elmira College -- 9-page letter discussing his studies and critiquing of concerts (Box-folder 1: 7)
    - Letter and envelope: February 14, 1904 --Written to Miss Mary Selena Broughton at Elmira College -- 8-page letter discussing his studies and critiquing of concerts (Box-folder 1: 8)
    - Letter and envelope: February 26, 1904 -- Written to Miss Mary Selena Broughton --12-page letter critiquing concerts that he has attended (Box-folder 1: 9)
    - Letter and envelope: March 14, 1904 -- Written to Miss Mary Selena Broughton -- 10-page letter critiquing concerts and music, and discussing his daily activities [1904] (Box-folder 1: 10)
    - Letter and envelope: March 21, 1904 -- Written to Miss Mary Selena Broughton -- 4-page letter, First paragraph of letter written in Italian and the last page contains a list of performances written in German, for which Griffes is one (Box-folder 1: 11)
    - Letter and envelope: April 11, 1904 -- Written to Mis Mary Selena Broughton --3-page letter, primarily addressing the concerts he has attended [1904] (Box-folder 1: 12)
    - Letter and envelope: April 25, 1904 -- Written to Miss Mary Selena Broughton -- 3-page letter discussing his studies and daily activities (Box-folder 1: 13)
    - Letter: June 20, 1904 -- Written to Miss Mary Selena Broughton -- 3-page letter thanking Ms. Broughton for sending money (Box-folder 1: 14)
    - Letter and envelope: August 7, 1904 -- Written to his mother -- 12-page letter primarily focused on a trip throughout Germany, mentions that Ms. Broughton is visiting (Box-folder 1: 15)
    - Letter and envelope: August 14, 1904 -- Written to his mother -- 8-page letter, continued discussion of his trip through Germany, mainly concerning Dresden (Box-folder 1: 16)
    - Letter and envelope: August 21, 1904 -- Written to his mother -- 7-page letter, continued discussion of his trip through Germany and visit to home and haunts of Johann Sebastian Bach (Box-folder 1: 17)
    - Letter and envelope: September 26, 1904 -- Written to Miss Mary Selena Broughton -- 8-page letter concerning her trip to Germany, and containing a description of his musical training and daily practice schedule (Box-folder 1: 18)
    - Letter and envelope: October 19, 1904 -- Written to Miss Mary Selena Broughton -- 9-page letter, primarily discussing the current happenings, reference to his muisc tutelage is a minimal (Box-folder 1: 19)
    - Letter and envelope: October 24, 1904 -- Written to his mother -- 6-page letter, giving an update on his musical studies and concerts that he has attended (Box-folder 1: 20)
    - Letter and envelope: November 20, 1904 -- Written to Miss Mary Selena Broughton -- 6-page letter primarily discussing a Wanda Landowska concert, also mentioning his own musical progress (Box-folder 1: 21)
    - Letter and envelope: January 1, 1905 -- Written to Miss Mary Selena Broughton -- 8-page letter discussing his future prospects for living and continuing to study in Europe (Box-folder 1: 22)
    - Letter and envelope: February 12, 1905 -- Written to his mother -- 6-page letter discussing his desire to remain in Europe another year to continue his music study, his desire to learn more about composition (1: 23)
    - Letter and envelope: May 22, 1905 --Written to Miss Mary Selena Broughton -- 8-page letter concerned with a visit to the Landon's, also includes talk of the advancement in his studies (Box-folder 1: 24)
    - Letter and envelope: October 28, 1905 -- Written to Miss Mary Selena Broughton -- 4-page letter telling of his acceptance as Engelbert Humperdinck's pupil (1: 25)
    - Letter and envelope: January 21, 1906 -- Written to Miss Mary Selena Broughton -- 6-page letter discussing his training under Humperdinck, his efforts at composing and his study of Mozart (Box-folder 1: 26)
    - Letter and envelope: September 9, 1906 -- Written to his mother -- 6-page letter mentioning his two pupils (Box-folder 1: 27)
    - Letter and envelope: October 28, 1906 -- Written to his mother-- 6-page letter discussing his daily activities, including his position as instructor (Box-folder 1: 28)
  - SUB-SERIES 2: MISCELLANEOUS PAPERS, 1903 - 1917; SUB-SERIES NOTE: This sub-series contains transcripts of diary entries not found in the correspondence from the above sub-series, two drawings from Griffes’ time in Europe and six photographs. The photographs capture Griffes from childhood to adulthood. The sub-series is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
    - Diary -- Transcript, July 4-August 29, 1904 (Box-folder 1: 29)
    - Diary and Berlin Letters -- Transcript, Entries from September 18, 1903 to October 17, 1917 ( transcripts are not from letters 2:1:1-27), 1903 - 1917 (Box-folder 1: 30)
    - Drawings -- Cityscape sketch and a watercolor sketch of drubeck, July, 1904 (Box-folder 1: 31)
    - Photographs -- Professional black and white photographs from youth to adulthood, 1 oversize photo in OS1:1, 1904-1917 (Box-folder 1 :32)
    - Specimens, Floral -- A number of pressed floral pieces mounted on paper, 1904-1917 (Box-folder 1: 33)
- SERIES 2: SHEET MUSIC, 1898 - 1929; SERIES NOTE: The bulk of this series are original handwritten manuscripts, most include orchestration for multiple instruments. The series is arranged alphabetically.
  - Lament Manuscript -- For various instruments, manuscript, 1898-1929 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - "Opus 2: Six Variations in B flat major" and "Four preludes, Opus 40" -- composition notebook, written in 1898 (Gift of Harrison Potter), 1898 - 1900 (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - The Pleasure-Dome of Kubla Khan Orchestral Score -- Published by G. Schirmer, 1920 (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - The Pleasure-Dome of Kubla Khan, Orchestration Revised by Frederick A. Stock -- Published by G. Schirmer, 1929 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - Reveillon Manuscript -- Arranged by Myron Fink, manuscript, 1898-1929 (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - La Reveillon, The Rose of the Night, Lament -- Manuscript notebook, 1898-1929 (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - Rose of the Night Manuscript, 1898-1929 (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - Shojo Manuscript -- For various instruments, manuscript, 1898-1929 (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - Sonata, White Peacock, Lake at Evening -- Manuscript notebook, 1898-1929 (Box-folder 3: 9)
  - "Songs, misc." -- Binder of miscellaneous reproductions of musical scores, includes: "The Rose of the Night," "Si Mes Vers Avaient Des Ailes," and "Shojo", 1898-1929 (Box-folder 3: 10)
- SERIES 3: BOOKS FROM GRIFFES’ LIBRARY, 1859 - 1913; SERIES NOTE: The books in this series are from Griffes’ home library and have been arranged alphabetically by language of origination.
  - SUB-SERIES 1: ENGLISH, 1859 - 1913
    - Dieulafoy, Marcel: Art in Spain and Portugal, New York, Charles Scribner's Sons, 1913 [English]
    - Duffield, Samuel W.: English Hymns, 2nd Ed, Funk and Wagnalls, 1886? [English]
    - Hueffer, Ford Madox: The Pre-Raphaelite Brotherhood, London, Duckworth & Co.; New York, E. P. Dutton & Co., undated [English], 1859-1913
    - Irving, Washington: The Works of Washington Irving, Vol. V, London, Henry G. Bohn, 1859 [English]
    - Parker, John Henry, 1808-1884: A Concise Glossary of Terms used in Grecian, Roman, Italian, and Gothic Architecture, 9th Ed. Revised, Oxford and London, James Parker and Co., 1896 [English]
    - Parker, John Henry, 1808-1884: An Introduction to the Study of Gothic Architecture, 6th Ed., Oxford and London, Parker and Co., 1881 [English]
    - Raven, J. J.: The Bells of England, New York, E. P. Dutton & Co., 1906 [English]
    - Street, George Edmund: Some Account of Gothic Architecture in Spain, London, John Murray, 1869 [English]
  - SUB-SERIES 2: FRENCH, 1836- 1917, undated
    - Beaumarchais, Pierre Augustin Caron de: Theatre de Beaumarchais, Paris, Firmin-Didot et Cie, Imprimeurs-Editeurs, undated [French], 1836- 1917
    - Campan, Madame: Memoires sur la vie de Marie-Antoinette reine de france et de navarre suivis sede souvenirs et anecdotes historiques sur les regnes de Louis XIV, de Louis XV et de Louis XVI, Paris, Firmin-Didot Et C,ie, Imprimeurs-Editeurs, undated [French], 1836- 1917
    - Clement, Charles: Michel-Ange, Leonard De Vinci, Raphael: avec une etude sur l'art en Italie avant le XVI siecle et des catalogues raisonnes historiques et bibliographiques, Paris, Hetzel, 1875 [French]
    - Diehl, Charles: Dans l'orient Byzantin, Paris, Boccard, 1917 [French]
    - Duruy, V.: Historie de France, Tome I, Paris, Librairie de L. Hachette et Cie, 1860 [French]
    - Duruy, V.: Historie de France, Tome II, Paris, Librairie de Hachette et Cie, 1860 [French]
    - Dussault :Les Caracteres de A Bruyere suivis des caracteres de theophraste, traduits du grec par le meme, Paris, Librairie D'Abel Ledoux, 1836 [French]
    - France, Anatole: Le Crime de Sylvestre Bonnard, Paris, Calmann-Levy, Editeurs, undated [French], 1836- 1917
    - Gautier, Theophile: Le Roman de la momie, Paris, Bibliotheque-Charpentier, 1910 [French]
    - Goncourt, Edmond de: Hokousai, Paris, Bibliotheque-Charpentier, 1916 [French]
    - Goncourt, Edmond de: Outamaro, Paris, Bibliotheque-Charpentier, 1911 [French]
    - Labat, Jean-Baptiste: Nouveau Voyage Aux Isles de L-amerique, Tom. 4, Paris, Guillaume Cavelier, 1722 [French]
    - Lamartine, A. De: Harmonies, Poetiques, et Religieuses, Paris, Hachette et Cie, Jouvet Et Cie, editeurs, 1886 [French]
    - Lepelletier, Edmond: Paul Verlaine, Paris, Societe dv Mercvre de France, 1907 [French]
    - Merimee, Prosper: Carmen, Paris, Michel Levy Freres, Editeurs, 1875 [French]
    - Mignet, M.: Antonio Perez et Philippe II, Paris, Charpenter, Libraire-Editeur, 1854 [French]
    - Montesquieu: Lettres Persanes suivies de arsace et usmenie et de pensees diverses par Montesquieu, Paris, Garnier Freres, Libraires-Editeurs, undated [French], 1836- 1917
    - Nolhac, Pierre de: La Reine Marie-Antoinette, Paris, Calmann-Levy, Editeurs, undated [French], 1836- 1917
    - Nolhac, Pierre de: Marie-Antoinette Dauphine d'apres de nouveaux documents, Paris, Calmann-Levy, Editeurs, undated [French], 1836- 1917
    - Reinaud, M.: Relation Des voyages faits par les arabes et les persans dans l'inde et a la chine dans le ix siecle de l'ere chretienne text arabe imprime en 1811 par les soins de feu langles, Paris, A L'imprimerie royale, 1845 [French]
    - Reinaud, M.: Relation Des Voyages Faits Par Les Arabes Et Les Persans Dans L'Inde Et A La Chine Dans Le Siecle De L'ere Chretienne, Paris, A L'imprimerie Royale, 1845 [French]
    - Sand, George: Lucrezia Floriani Lavinia, Paris, Ancienne Maison Michel Levy Freres, 1880 [French]
    - Vasi, M.; Rectifie par A. Nibby: Itineraire instructif de Rome ancienne et moderne, ou Description generale des monumens antiques et modernes, et des ouvrages les plus remarquables en peinture, sculpture et architecture de cette celebre ville et de ses environs, Vol. 1, A. Rome, Chez l' Auteur, 1818 [French]
    - Vasi, M.; Rectifie par A. Nibby: Itineraire instructif de Rome ancienne et moderne, ou Description generale des monumens antiques et modernes, et des ouvrages les plus remarquables en peinture, sculpture et architecture de cette celebre ville et de ses environs, Vol. 2, A. Rome, Chez l' Auteur, 1818 [French]
  - SUB-SERIES 3: GERMAN, 1863?-1913?, undated
    - Bader, Karl: Turm und Glockenbuchlein: Eine Wanderung durch deutsche Wachter und Glockenstuben, Giessen, J. Ricker's Verlag, 1903 [German]
    - Bertels, Kurt: Francisco Goya, Munchen und Leipzig, R. Piper & Co., 1907 [German]
    - Gieb, Carl: Die Sagen und Geschichten des Rheinlandes, Frankfurt, Carl Jugel's Verlag, 1880 [German]
    - Gietmann, Gerhard: Asthetik der Baukunst, Friedburg, Herdersche, 1903 [German]
    - Frey, Ludwig: Der Eros und die Kunst, Leipzig Berlag von Mar Epohr, undated [German], 1863?-1913?
    - Hafiz: Diwan Des Grossen Lyrischen Dichters, Hafis, Im Persischen Original Herausgegeben ins Deutsche Metrisch Ubersetzt und Mit Anmerkungen Versehen, Wien, Druck Und Verlag Der K. K. Hof Und Staatsdruckerei, 1864 [German]
    - Hamann, Richard: Die Fruh-Renaissance Der italienischen Malerei: 200 Nachbildungen Mitgeschichtlicher Einfuhrung und Erlauterungen, Jena, Verlegt Bei Eugen Diederichs, 1909 [German]
    - Heilmann, Hans: Chinesische lyrik vom 12 jahrhundert v. Chr. Bis zur gegenwart; in deutscher abersetzung, mit einleitung und anmerkungen, Munchen, R. Piper, undated [German], 1863?-1913?
    - Heine, Heinrich: Letzte Gedichte, Halle, Verlag von Otto Hendel, undated [German], 1863?-1913?
    - Heine, Heinrich: Neue Gedichte, Halle, Verlag von Otto Hendel, undated [German], 1863?-1913?
    - Pinder, Wilhelm: Deutsche Dome Des Mittelalters, Verlag, Dusseldorf, Leipzig, Karl Robert Langewiesche, 1913 ? [German]
    - Schonhuth, Ottmar Friedrich Heinrich: Die burgen, kloster, kirchen & Kapellen Wurttembergs und der presussisch hohenzolern schen landestheile, mit ihren geschichten, sagen und mahrchen, 1-5, Stuttgart, E. Fischhaber, 1863? [German]
    - Wolzogen, Ernst Von: Kraft-Mayr: ein humoristischer musikan ten-roman, Stuttgart, J. Engelhorn, 1897 [German]
  - SUB-SERIES 4: ITALIAN, 1768-1911
    - Annunzio, Gabriele d': Francesca da Rimini, Milan, Treves bros., 1902 [Italian]
    - Borghini, Raffaello: Il riposo di Raffaello Borghini, Milan, Dalla Societa Tipografica de Classici Italiani, 1807 [Italian]
    - Borghini, Raffaello: Il Riposo Di Raffaello Borghini, Vol. Secondo, Milano, Dalla Societa Tipografica de Classica Italiani, 1807 [Italian]
    - Borghini, Raffaello: Il Riposo Di Raffaello Borghini, Vol. Terza, Milano, Dalla Societa Tipografica de Classica Italiani, 1807 [Italian]
    - Goldoni, Carlo: Scelte Commedie, Vol. IV, Milano, Antonio Fontana, 1826 [Italian]
    - Guarini, Giovanni Battista: Il Pastor Fido, Parigi, Appresso Prauls, 1768 [Italian]
    - Leopardi, Giacomo: I Canti, Milano, Ulrico Hoepli, Editore-Libraio Della Real Casa, 1911 [Italian]
    - Petrarca, Francesco: Le rime… nuova edizione, Avignone, Seguin, 1812 (2 vol.) [Italian]
    - Saldani, Redi: Ditirambici e satirici del secolo XVII, Redi Soldani e Ros Menzini, Venezia, Zattae, 1879 [Italian]